<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Modern Apprenticeship</title>
    <description>Modern Apprenticeship blog by Paul Pagel</description>
    <link>http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>How can we teach humility?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A craftsman’s journey to mastery never ends. A craftsman will never run out of opportunities for improvement. Because of this reality, it’s important that craftsmen remain humble students, forever improving their craft without becoming overzealous nor overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lesson proves to be a difficult one to introduce in a modern apprenticeship. Whereas practices and skills highlight a craft’s explicit knowledge, humility is what’s called tacit knowledge—it’s a lesson that you can observe, but cannot easily transfer from one person to another through lessons or books. A mentor cannot teach humility: a mentor can only provide opportunities for the apprentice to acquire it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular example of this process comes from the 1984 film “Karate Kid.” At the beginning of Daniel LaRusso’s apprenticeship, Mr. Miyagi made LaRusso wax his car and paint his fence. LaRusso felt used, and resented Mr. Miyagi for using him for manual labor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Mr. Miyagi revealed his intentions. By waxing and painting exactly as Miyagi had instructed, LaRusso had already internalized the basic motions of a proper self defense. Miyagi flipped the two different concepts of knowledge: he made his implicit teachings (humility) explicit, and his explicit teachings (defensive maneuvers) implicit. Upon revealing this paradox, he achieved something profound in his student. LaRusso’s frustration was funneled into humility and appreciation for the skills he’d learned, as well as respect for the one who taught them to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paradoxical approach is atypical, though. Traditionally, mentors have sought to teach humility by increasing the apprentice’s workload; by making the apprentice buckle underneath the gravity of their craft. Apprentices performed the menial tasks that freed their mentors to perform their craft at its highest level. Then, they would then benefit from working in this same environment, and by receiving lessons from a craftsman who is performing a craft at its highest level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our model of modern apprenticeship at 8th Light has always tried to implement a similar policy toward teaching humility. Apprentices are responsible for office upkeep—loading and unloading the dishwasher; taking out the garbage; setting up, recording, and cleaning up after 8th Light University events; and performing regular small talks for student apprentices; in addition to other miscellaneous tasks that come up in our office. They do the work that creates an ideal working environment for our craftsmen and for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last summer, we moved to a new office that has required an even greater commitment to the miscellaneous tasks of office upkeep. Apprentices were responsible for organizing and unpacking much of our office furniture and supplies. They assembled tables and chairs, set up monitors and A/V equipment, and continued performing their same daily duties across an office that had doubled in size. Throughout this transition, the academic rigors of their apprenticeship were ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this made me question whether our apprenticeship program was still teaching humility effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As tacit knowledge, humility is demonstrated through service. But although adding another rock to somebody’s backpack can build character, it can also have an adverse effect. Every time you volunteer someone else for a task, you’re treating humility like explicit knowledge that can be taught. And when you fill someone’s day with menial labor, you open yourself to resentment unless you can prove its utility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I think it’s so important to ask whether we’re teaching humility effectively. The best way to teach tacit knowledge is by demonstrating it for others to observe and absorb. Are you teaching humility by being of service to others?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/featured/2015/02/20/teaching-humility/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/featured/2015/02/20/teaching-humility/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Type of Learner Are You?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships are immersive experiences that should consume all of an apprentice’s attention. They require a steady and unwavering dedication to practice. But it’s unrealistic to think that even the most driven apprentices don’t have multiple interests outside of their chosen craft. Everybody has hobbies that we do for reasons other than a humble pursuit of mastery. They entertain us, they distract us, and they can even refuel us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his popular book Mastery, George Leonard outlined four types of learners that I’ve listed below. He presents three of these learners as character profiles of people who enter a craft with the wrong mental approach, and uses these descriptions to help diagnose and explain reasons why a particular learner will fail on their path to mastery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think it’s helpful to take such a pessimistic view of these descriptions, because I don’t think we should take such a singular view of learning. We are all different types of learners for different crafts, and it’s healthy to take these different roles in different areas of our lives. It helps broaden our perspective, and can be a useful leisure activity that allows us to approach our chosen craft each day with renewed vigor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dabbler&quot;&gt;The Dabbler&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any naturally curious person has dabbled in several different interests. In my lifetime, I’ve spent time learning to make coffee and building small woodworking projects just to satiate some inner curiosity about these crafts. I’m not an expert in either of them, but I’m content with my surface-level comprehension. I’m a novice in many different crafts, and I think this broad familiarity is beneficial. We all need hobbies that are relaxing and fun without requiring an intense attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hacker&quot;&gt;The Hacker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone has their sights set on accomplishing a large goal, she or he is likely to become a hacker in a handful of crafts that stand in the way of that goal. Many people who attend code schools or who take online software classes are learning to code not for their vocation, but because they understand the role software can play in achieving their goals. There are always hurdles between where you are and where you want to be, and oftentimes it’s sufficient to be a hacker in them and learn only as much as you need to in order to get past them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began hacking as an entrepreneur so that I could achieve my goal of providing a software consultancy that was built on the pillars of software craftsmanship. But while I learned more about business and built my company, I began appreciating the nuance and the process of business management. That’s when I began creating something like an apprenticeship for myself. I joined the Entrepreneurs’ Organization to surround myself with mentors, and entered the Executive Masters of Business program at Northwestern University’s Kellogg School of Management to continue on my path toward mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-obsessive&quot;&gt;The Obsessive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, we’re obsessive about things that appeal to our competitive drives. The quest is to come out ahead in something, and the drive is internal and self-motivated. When I register to run a marathon, I’m extremely motivated to train for that marathon. I run obsessively. I buy sports equipment that will help me conquer the goal. But when the marathon is over, I no longer feel motivated to run. I loved running while I had something competitive to look forward to; but once that competitive drive was gone, so was my interest in seeking improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-apprentice&quot;&gt;The Apprentice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible for you to be different character types for different crafts, and it is also possible for you to transition from one character type to another within the same craft. If you dabble in a field for long enough, you might encounter a study that inspires you to pursue that craft. Some of 8th Light’s craftsmen began learning to code while pursuing an older craft, only to discover their passion for writing code. It is also possible to begin learning a craft as competition, only to be awestruck and prompted to dive into an apprenticeship to learn it for its own sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path to mastery is a challenging and demanding task that never ends. It’s a massive commitment, and we don’t need to make it every time we pick up a hobby. &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/featured/2015/02/02/types-of-learners/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/featured/2015/02/02/types-of-learners/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using the Availability Bias</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The more you practice using a certain tool or skill, the more comfortable you become performing it. You build up muscle memory, and the motions become automatic. You can focus on more challenging topics. If you can repeat keystrokes without exhausting conscious effort on writing software, then you have that much more energy and attention available to devote to more advanced and abstract concerns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This automation process is extremely helpful, and allows our brains to operate on more challenging issues as we work toward mastery. But relying on the information our brains supply for us leaves us vulnerable to its subtle shortcomings; sometimes the solution that presents itself automatically isn’t the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These shortcomings can be summed up as the Availability Bias, in which we assign inflated confidence to the information that readily presents itself to us. In order to avoid the traps of a logical fallacy like this, it helps to understand how it’s created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our brains can only store a limited amount of information at any one time. Names, faces, dates, and places get shuffled around and lost in our heads in order to make room for new information every day. These limitations are even more imposing on the number of thoughts and memories that are immediately accessible through our working memories. We can’t hoard memories—our brains are constantly sifting through and discarding pieces of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent literature suggests there’s an evolutionary motor behind this process. Current theories propose that, because we were born with physical restrictions on how much information we can store in our brains, they come equipped with a natural updating mechanism that ensures we’re only carrying information that continues to be relevant. Studies have shown that whenever we recall a memory, the details that were unimportant to us do not appear in future recalls of the same memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For long-term memory, that means we forget the names of people we went to school with and haven’t thought about in years; or we consolidate several memories about different recess periods into a single one that is more compact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For short-term or working memory, that means the information readily available to us is the information that has proven itself to be useful in similar situations recently. Our brains gather sensory information to prepare and front-load a pool of information that it thinks will be advantageous. If we’re baking a cake, our working memory loads everything we know about measuring, mixing, and baking to our awareness. Our mind frame shifts with each new task, carrying over the tools that we’ve needed in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working, we rely on this process to help us solve problems quickly and easily. It is an exceedingly helpful shortcut that we would struggle without. It allows us to practice certain skills until they are automatic, and then rely on those skills to operate well without expending energy thinking about them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this process of relying on connections that we’ve made in the past assumes that they will remain consistent with the problems we will face in the future. Every time we approach a new problem, we’ve already made assumptions about its answer. We arrive at every new problem with one arm tied behind our back (or, with the majority of our knowledge distant and inaccessible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how we fall victim to the Availability Bias. In our attempt to automate a portion of labor, our problem solving skills forfeit some amount of scrutiny. But if we acknowledge that this bias exists, we can confront it and take advantage of it in two ways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.
We should actively seek out and learn new information that is irrelevant to our work. By learning new information that exists far away from what we are doing, we can disrupt the comfort zone created by our working memory and force ourselves to consider new ideas. While we’re learning new information, we can look for ways to fold this new information into our existing contexts. For example: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.8thlight.com/kevin-buchanan/2014/08/20/functional-ish-ruby.html&quot;&gt;if we practice Clojure, we can look for ways to incorporate techniques from its functional paradigm into our Ruby code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those kinds of connections are impossible unless we force an overlap between separate, unrelated paradigms. When our available context is broadened, we allow ourselves the potential to spark new connections and ideas that change the way we think for the better. We teach our brains to recognize that a wider swath of knowledge is advantageous in each given setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.
We should be revisiting old information regularly. Most professionals return to old materials to refresh themselves before jumping into a new project, but there’s utility to this practice even during times when you don’t anticipate needing to use the new information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the biggest appeals of mentorship. Teaching a topic to someone else requires that you have total comprehension. Before teaching a lesson, you’ll need to return to the material and reacquaint yourself with its details. This reminds your brain what it already knows, and helps keep the information fresh and easily accessible to your subconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentoring others isn’t entirely altruistic. Mentorship helps us maintain a close relationship with our tools and skills, and thus ensures our working memories remain ours to take advantage of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that we can never fully anticipate what problems we’ll encounter in our work, and we can’t stretch our working memories wide enough to include everything we might possibly need to know. But by acknowledging the Availability Bias and deliberately diversifying the types of practices and lessons that float around in our mind, we can make sure that the information that presents itself to us is at least representative of a larger sample of our brains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/2015/01/12/using-availability-bias/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://modern-apprenticeship.8thlight.com/2015/01/12/using-availability-bias/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
